A Guide to the Papers of the Madden Family, 1760-1874
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Madden Family, 1760-1874
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
4120
This collection consists of ca. 396 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited on 1953 Jan 6.
Scope and Content Information
This microfilm collection (M-589), 1760-1874, ca. 396 items, consists of documents discovered by T. O. [Thomas Obed] Madden, Jr., in his great-great-grandmother's (Sarah Madden) trunk in 1949 concerning this Virginia free black family ("Free Negro"). Many are reproduced, cited or described in T. O. Madden, Jr., We Were Always Free: The Maddens of Culpeper County, Virginia(New York: Norton, 1992). Researchers should consult this book while using the collection. Initially placed on deposit for safekeeping and historical reference in the Library by Mr. T. O. Madden, Jr., Elkwood, Culpeper County, Virginia, on January 6, 1953, the collection was returned to him on March 13, 1953 after its microfilming. However, ten items (four originals and six negative photostatic copies) remain in the control folder. Microfilm and control folder listings are appended at the end of this guide.
Most of the collection pertains to Willis Madden (1799-1879) of Culpeper County, son of Sarah Madden (1758-1824), the illegitimate mulatto daughter of Mary Madden, an unmarried Irish woman of St. George's Parish, Spotsylvania County. Sarah became an indentured servant in the household of George Fraser, a merchant Scot who resided in Spotsylvania County, from 1760 to his death in 1765, the household of James Madison, Sr. (father of the president), Montpelier, Orange County, 1767 to 1783, and Francis Madison (brother of the president), Culpeper County, 1783 to 1789. Her son Willis (tenth of Sarah's thirteen children) later became the patriarch of one of Virginia's most prosperous antebellum free black families. In 1823 he began securing written references from his white neighbors and by 1835 had purchased nearly ninety acres upon which he built a home, tavern, and a general store. Over the next thirty years he became a moderately prosperous tavern keeper and farmer. Madden's Tavern was placed on the Virginia Landmarks Register and on the National Register of Historic Places in 1984 [Madden, We Were Always Free; Calder Loth, Virginia Landmarks of Black History(Charlottesville and London: University Press of Virginia, 1995), 111-113].
Items of interest include: an April 17, 1760 apprenticeship indenture for Sarah Madden's indentured servitude to George Fraser for thirty-one years; genealogical information (chiefly birth lists); a June 12, 1823 letter of Culpeper County justice George Fitzhugh to Captain Thomas Humphries attesting to the Madden family's good character and advising them against having any contact with slaves; certificates of freedom for Willis Madden and his wife Katherine "Kitty" Clark Madden (September 23, 1822 and September 19, 1826); a deed, October 13, 1835, by which Martin and Mary Slaughter sell Willis Madden eighty-seven acres of land in Culpeper County; correspondence (primarily of Sarah and Willis Madden). Assorted financial and legal papers include personal receipts, promissory notes, state and county tax receipts, store accounts, Sarah Madden's account book (ca. 1797-ca. 1799) of her work as a laundress and seamstress; Mariah Madden (daughter of Willis) items, and Willis Madden's Civil War damage claims (1871-1873). A few items pertain to the Clark family, in-laws of the Maddens.
Contents List
- Microfilms
  - Genealogy [n.d.], ca. 27 items
  - Documents 1823-1849, ca. 26 items
  - Tax Receipts 1852-1865, ca. 30 items
  - Accounts of Sarah Madden 1792, 1796, ca. 15 items
  - Accounts 1800-1839, ca. 12 items
  - Accounts 1840's, ca. 56 items
  - Accounts 1850-1854, ca. 72 items
  - Accounts 1855-1859, ca. 92 items
  - Accounts ca. 32 items, 1860's
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts No Date, ca. 24 items
- Original Documents.
  Note: The four original documents in the control folder (December 17, 1822, May 16, [1853], May 30, 1874, and September 12, 1874) are not on Microfilm 589.
  - Thomas Walker Lightfoot, clerk, Culpeper County Court, free (registration) papers of Kitty Clark (wife of Willis Madden) and F[ayette] Mauzy receipt for Willis Madden, "To the Clerk of Culpeper/To be order certifying the heir of Hannah Clark 44 seals to pension papers of same 74" 1822 Sep 23 & 1848
  - Receipt, "James R. [Field?] Three dollars and sixty-eight cents in settlement.... my hand this 17 day of Dec 1822/Willis Madden" 1822 Dec 17, [original]
  - Account, "Uncle Willis Madden [Bought] of J. W. [ ? awby]," 257 pounds of iron, $15.50, "charged to account" [1853] May 16, [original]
  - Account of Willis Madden with G[eorge] W. Stone, $16.17 1874 May 30, [original; Madden, p. 121]
  - Account/receipt of Delewar Carter & Washington Blair with Thomas Wood, $4.92 1874 Sep 12, [original]